Guide to the Annina Nosei Gallery Archive 1963-2009 MSS.298
Fales Library and Special Collections
Annina Nosei Gallery Archive
1963-2009
Fales Library and Special Collections
Nosei, Annina
MSS.298
74.2 Linear Feet in 136 boxes
The Annina Nosei Gallery was a New York City art gallery from 1981 to 2005. The Annina Nosei Gallery Archive comprises the records produced and used by the gallery; it also includes records of Annina Nosei's private acquisitions and sales, as well as her work as a curator/dealer before and after the Annina Nosei Gallery.
Biographical / Historical
Based in SoHo for fifteen years, Annina Nosei Gallery moved to Chelsea in 1995, closing in 2005. The gallery was instrumental in introducing the work of Neo Expressionist Italian and German figurative painters, as well as young American painters, to a market largely dominated by minimalism and conceptual art. From its inception until its closing in 2005, the Annina Nosei Gallery continued to promote young, emerging artists.
Annina Nosei was born in Rome, Italy. She received doctorates in literature and philosophy from the University of Rome, where she studied under the art historian Giulian Carlo Argan and wrote her thesis on Marcel Duchamp. She received a Fulbright in 1964 to study in the United States, where she taught at the University of Michigan and later at UCLA, St. John's University in Manhattan, and Kingsborough Community College in Brooklyn.
While teaching at UCLA in 1965, Nosei met the art dealer John Weber, to whom she was married from 1966 to 1973. Her first gallery experience was in helping to organize and install exhibitions at Weber's gallery in Los Angeles. In 1979, Nosei began to show and deal art in a loft owned by Larry Gagosian at 421 West Broadway, New York City, across the street from the Leo Castelli Gallery. In 1980, Nosei opened her own gallery in SoHo at 100 Prince Street. In 1995, the gallery moved to 530 West 22nd Street, in Chelsea, and closed in 2005.
Nosei is known for being the first dealer to represent Jean-Michel Basquiat from 1981 to about 1983, and for providing him with materials and a space to work in the basement of the gallery. Though known primarily for representing German and American Neo-Expressionists and Italian New Image painters, the Annina Nosei Gallery represented and exhibited a diverse range of artists, such as Ghada Amer, Julio Galan, Tsibi Geva, Graciela Hasper, Barbara Kruger, Robert Longo, Alan McCollum, Shirin Neshat, and Jenny Watson.
Sources:
Chernow, Burt. (2000). Christo and Jeanne-Claude: a biography. New York: St. Martin's Press.
(2002). The New York Times Guide to the Arts of the 20th Century, Vol. IV, 1980-1989. Chicago: Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers.
Krantz, Les. (1985). American art galleries: the illustrated guide to thir art and artists. New York: Facts on File Publications.
Private communication with Annina Nosei, March 16, 2011.
Smith, Roberta. (June 1, 2008). "John Weber, 75, Contemporary-Art Dealer, Is Dead." The New York Times. From http://www.nytimes.com/2008/06/01/arts/design/01weber.html
Thompson, Donald N. (2008). The $12 million stuffed shark: the curious economics of contemporary art. London: Aurum Press.
de Coppet, L. & Jones, A. (1984). The Art Dealers. New York: Cooper Square Press.
Arrangement
Series were created by the archivist based on discussions with Annina Nosei and on a careful appraisal of the material. Each series reflects an explicit function of the Annina Nosei Gallery in its daily activities of taking artworks on consignment; of buying, selling, and shipping artworks; of planning and executing exhibitions in its gallery space as well as at museums, art fairs, and other galleries; and of managing, promoting, and paying represented artists. Every effort was made to retain the original order of the files. The subseries reflect the titles and organization of records by the gallery.
Almost all subseries titles were originated by the gallery as it created and maintained its records (and were printed on hanging files in labeled file cabinet drawers or on labeled boxes). The following four subseries were created and named by the archivist in an effort to simplify access, protect materials, and organize miscellany:
Series III, Subseries D
Series III, Subseries E
Series IV, Subseries G
Series VII, Subseries C
Folders: Original folders were replaced with acid-free folders. Unless in brackets, all folder titles are taken from the original folder. A folder label in brackets is a label supplied by the archivist, either because the material was not foldered or because the original folder was unlabeled. The archivist has striven to replicate the gallery's naming conventions where they could be discerned.
Each folder in the archive holds the entire contents of an original folder. If there was more material in an original folder than would fit in a new folder, that material is divided between two or more folders, each folder bearing the original folder's name followed by the convention "[1/4]," "[2/4]," etc. If two different folders share the same name, each will be followed by a number in brackets denoting its position in a series/subseries (e.g., "[1]," "[2]," etc.).
Binders: Unless in brackets, all binder labels are taken from the original binders. All materials separated from binders are foldered according to their original grouping in a single binder sleeve (most of which contained several items).
Photocopies: All thermal paper has been replaced with a photocopied surrogate. Original folders bearing writing have been photocopied, and the photocopy has been placed at the end of the new folder. Items bearing sticky notes were photocopied, the sticky notes were removed, and the photocopies refiled with the originals (usually attached to it with a plastic clip).
Dates: All dates are approximate and provided by the archivist based on a cursory glance at the contents of each folder.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Scope and Content
The Annina Nosei Gallery Archive comprises the records produced by the Annina Nosei Gallery in the day-to-day course of its business functions. The archive also includes records of Annina Nosei's private acquisitions and sales, as well as her work as a curator/dealer before and after the Annina Nosei Gallery. Materials include invoices and receipts for works bought and sold by the gallery or by Annina Nosei personally; administrative records for the Annina Nosei Gallery; photographic prints, transparancies, slides, and negatives; correspondence with artists, dealers, collectors, critics, curators, and other art institutions; promotional and exhibition materials (artist bios, magazine advertisements, exhibition announcements), and periodicals and clippings that feature artists represented by the gallery.
Series Description The Annina Nosei Gallery Archive is divided into nine series.
Series I: Transaction Records comprises files created in the gallery's process of buying artworks, taking artworks on consignment, and selling artworks. The series is divided into ten subseries.
Subseries A: Consignment Files
Subseries B: Inventory Cards: Works Sold
Subseries C: Inventory Cards: Returned to Artist
Subseries D: Inventory Books
Subseries E: Collector's Books
Subseries F: Artist Books
Subseries G: Acquisitions Receipts
Subseries H: Invoices
Subseries I: Shipment Records
Subseries J: Accounting
Series II: Correspondence comprises correspondence sent and received by the Annina Nosei Gallery. The series is divided into five subseries.
Subseries A: Collectors
Subseries B: Dealers
Subseries C: Museum and Universities
Subseries D: Art Fairs/Auction Houses
Subseries E: Magazines, Critics, and Curators
Series III: Artist Files comprises paper documents (including artists' bios, price lists, clippings, correspondence, exhibition announcements) and photographic materials relating to artists represented by the gallery and shows held at the gallery. The series is divided into six subseries.
Subseries A: General Artist Files
Subseries B: Master Slides Binders
Subseries C: Visuals Binders
Subseries D: Material Separated from Master Slides Binders
Subseries E: Material Separated from Visuals Binders
Subseries F: Polaroids
Series IV: Jean-Michel Basquiat Artist File comprises artist biographies and other promotional material, price lists, invoices, correspondence, phone bills, bank account records, photographic material, and periodicals and clipping relating to Jean-Michel Basquiat, his work, and his relationship with the Annina Nosei Gallery. The series is divided into ten subseries.
Subseries A: Artist Files
Subseries B: Correspondence
Subseries C: Accounting
Subseries D: Invoices
Subseries E: Slides Binder
Subseries F: Visuals Binders
Subseries G: Material Separated from Visuals Binders
Subseries H: Polaroids
Subseries I: Catalogs
Subseries J: Periodicals, Clippings
Series V: Exhibition Records comprises materials related to each show held at the Annina Nosei Gallery. Materials include installation photographs, price lists, artist bios, exhibition cards, press clippings. The series is divided into nine subseries.
Subseries A: Annina Nosei Gallery Shows; 1982-1983, 1983-1984
Subseries B: Annina Nosei Gallery Shows; September 1984 - August 1986
Subseries C: Annina Nosei Gallery Shows; October 1986 to December 1989 (included [sic]
Subseries D: Annina Nosei Gallery Shows; January 1990 - July 1992
Subseries E: Exhibitions; October 1992 - Jan 1993 - 94 - 96
Subseries F: Exhibitions Record; Jan 1997 - Dec 1999
Subseries G: Exhibition Records Jan. 2000 -
Subseries H: Catalogs
Subseries I: Guest Books
Series VI: Other Administrative Files comprises material related to the general day-to-day administration of the gallery itself and the gallery space. The series is divided into three subseries.
Subseries A: Planners
Subseries B: Memos
Subseries C: Gallery Space
Series VII: Pre-gallery Curating comprises material drawn from exhibitions curated by Nosei prior to opening her gallery.
Series VIII: Misc. Artist Publications, Periodicals, Clippings comprises some monographs of artists represented by the gallery, some periodicals that include artists represented by the gallery, and various clippings, all accumulated and stored by the gallery.
New Image.; SoHo (New York, N.Y.) -- Intellectual life.; Painters |y Italy.; Correspondence.; Slides (photographs); Negatives (photographic); SoHo (New York, N.Y.); Chelsea (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.) |v Exhibitions.; Art galleries (institutions); Painters |y Germany.; Art |x Management |z United States; Art |x Finance.; Art -- Exhibitions.; Chelsea (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); Painting, American -- 20th century.; Painters -- United States.; Color prints (photographs); Color photographs.; Neo-Expressionist.; Artists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Art, Modern -- United States -- 20th century.; Art, Modern -- 20th century -- Exhibitions.; Art, American -- New York (State) -- New York -- 21st century; Art, American -- New York (State) -- 20th century.; Art, American -- 20th century; Art |x Marketing.; Cannella, Piero Pizzi, 1955-; Brooks, Ellen, 1946-; Bowes, David, 1957-; Bowen, Nancy, 1955-; Tatafiore, Ernesto, 1943-; Duclos, Arturo, 1959-; Deutsch, David, 1943-; Connelly, Chuck, 1955-; Watson, Jenny, 1951-; Samba, Cheri, 1956-; Salomé, 1954-; Neshat, Shirin, 1957-; Mueller, Stephen, 1947-2011; Mirri, Sabina, 1957-; Middendorf, Helmut, 1953-; Kuitca, Guillermo, 1961-; Kruger, Barbara, 1945-; Hodicke, Karl Horst, 1938-; Glier, Mike, 1953-; Gallo, Vincent, 1961-; Galan, Julio, 1958-; Basquiat, Jean-Michel, 1960-1988; Ahearn, John, 1951-; Amer, Ghada, 1963-; Bedia Valdes, Jose, 1959-; Nosei, Annina
- Series I: Transaction Records, 1976-2006
  Scope and Content
  Series comprises files created in the gallery's process of buying works, taking works on consignment, and selling works.
  Arrangement
  The subseries reflect the gallery's original organization.
  - Subseries A: Consignment Files
    Subseries comprises files created by the gallery when taking works on consignment.
    Subseries is arranged in its original order.
    - Out on Consignment Inactive 83, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Out on Consignment; Inactive - 1983, 1980-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Xerox [1/2], 1978-1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Xerox [2/2], 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Press Mailing List [1/2], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Press Mailing List [2/2], 1986 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - In on Consignment. Ret. 86, 1982, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Out on Consignment - Inactive 1985 [1/3] (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Out on Consignment - Inactive 1985 [2/3], 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Out on Consignment - Inactive 1985 [3/3], 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Out on Consignment, Inactive 1984, 1979, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - In on Consignment - Returned 85, 1980, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - [Untitled Folder] [1/2], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Untitled Folder] [2/2], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Out on Consignment; Selected, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Out on Consignment Returned [1/2], 1993-2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Out on Consignment Returned [2/2], 1994-1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Selected in on [Consignment], 1982, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Consignments, 1987, 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Out on Consignmt Returned 1999/2000, '01, '02, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Out on Consmt. - Returned - 1998, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Subseries B: Inventory Cards: Works Sold
    Subseries comprises index cards created for each artwork sold by the gallery. Each card displays that artwork's inventory number and invoice number, which can also be found on corresponding records in this series. The cards are color coordinated.
    Pink card: The work was given to Annina Nosei, that is, she did not buy it. There was no money involved. On many of these cards you will find written the word "gift."
    Blue card: The work was bought by the Gallery. Most cards denote the amount paid.
    White card: The work was consigned to the gallery either by the artist, another dealer, another gallery, or a collector.
    Subseries is arranged in its original order. The index cards were originally contained in file drawers labeled "Works Sold" followed by an alphabetical range. This naming convention has been replicated here (e.g., the cards under the heading "Works Sold A-F" were originally held together in one file drawer labeled "Works Sold A-F"). The ranges of artists contained in each box has been provided by the archivist in the space below the box number.
    - Works Sold A-F [1/2], undated (Box 2)
      General
      John Ahearn-David Deutsch
    - Works Sold A-F [2/2], undated (Box 3)
      David Deutsch-Helmut Middendorf
    - Works Sold G-H-L, undated (Box 3)
    - Works Sold M-Z [1/2], undated (Box 3)
    - Works Sold M-Z [2/2], undated (Box 4)
      Helmut Middendorf-Michael Zwack
  - Subseries C: Inventory Cards: Returned to Artist
    Subseries comprises index cards created for each artwork that the gallery attempted to sell but could not and returned to the artist. Each card displays that artwork's inventory number, which can also be found on corresponding records in this series. The cards are color coordinated.
    Subseries is arranged in its original order. The index cards were originally contained in file drawers labeled "RTA" (which stands for "Returned to Artist") followed by an alphabetical range. This naming convention has been replicated here (e.g., the cards under the heading "RTA A-D-F" were originally held together in one file drawer labeled "RTA A-D-F"). The ranges of artists contained in each box has been provided by the archivist in the space below the box number.
    - RTA A-D-F [1/2], undated (Box 5)
      Gada Amer-Janieta Eyre
    - RTA A-D-F [2/2], undated (Box 6)
      Arturo Elizondo-Paul Mittleman
    - RTA G-M [1/2], undated (Box 6)
    - RTA G-M [2/2], undated (Box 7)
      Helmut Middendorf-Adriana Varejao
    - RTA N-Z [1/2], undated (Box 7)
    - RTA N-Z [2/2], undated (Box 8)
      Lucia Warck Meister-Zelli
  - Subseries D: Inventory Books
    Subseries is arranged in numerical order by inventory number. Folders are labeled with the title on front of the original ledger.
    Series comprises ten twelve-column ledgers organized by the inventory number assigned to each artwork. Each entry in each ledger gives the inventory number, the artist's name, the work's title, the date the work was received by the gallery, the year the work was executed, the size of the work, the artist's price, the consignee, the work's medium, the gallery's suggested price, amount owed to the gallery, and the work's current location including to whom it sold or if it was returned to the artist.
    - Inventory 1; #1 through #3949, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Inventory 2; #3950 through, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Gallery Inventory no. 1-5671, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Inventory, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Gallery Inventory no. 1019 through 6023, undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Gallery Inventory Book no 2; From #6024 through 7401, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Gallery Inventory Book no. 3; from #7402 through 8021, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Gallery Inventory Books no. 4; from #8022 to #8515, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Gallery Inventory Book no. 5; from #8516 to 9131, 1997-1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Gallery Inventory Book no. 6; from 9132 to 9703, 1999-2002 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Subseries E: Collector's Books
    According to the gallery, Collector's Books and Artist Books are different forms of the same function. At a cursory glance, Collector's Books comprises ledgers that seem to document what artist's work (by invoice number) was sold to what collector (whether individual or institution), while Artist Books comprises small spiral-bound notebooks listing the names, addresses, and phone numbers (sometimes in the form of business cards affixed to the pages) of persons and institutions interested in purchasing the work of certain artists. Often in Artist Books, a name and address will be accompanied by a note that reads "interested in 'X work of art'."
    The ledger sheets in Collector's Book A-I and Collector's Book J-O are from National brand top-lock post binders. Collecto'rs Book P-Z is from a Six Star brand top-lock post binder.
    Subseries is arranged in its original order. Ledger sheets were originally contained in large top-lock post binders and divided alphabetically by tabbed dividers. That arrangement has been replicated here at the folder level. The labels "Collector's Book A-I," "Collector's Book J-O," and "Collector's Book P-Z" were copied from labels on the binders themselves.
    - A [from "Collector's Book A through I"] [including photocopy of binder cover], 1981-1990 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - B [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1980-1993 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - C [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1992 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - D [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - E [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - F [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1995 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - G [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1990 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - H [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - I [from "Collector's Book A through I"], 1981-1994 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - J [from "Collector's Book J through O"] [including photocopy of binder cover], 1981-1990 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - K [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - L [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1981-1990 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - M [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Mc [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1980-1985 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - N [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - O [from "Collector's Book J through O"], 1981-1995 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - P, Q [from "Collector's Book P through Z"] [including photocopy of binder cover], 1981-1994 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - R [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - S [from "Collector's Book P through Z"] [1/2], 1980-1993 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - S [from "Collector's Book P through Z"] [2/2], 1981-1992 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - T [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1981-1991 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - U [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - V [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1981-1993 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - W [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1981-1991 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - YZ [from "Collector's Book P through Z"], 1981-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries F: Artist Books
    Subseries is arranged alphabetically by first artist's last name printed on the front of the book.
    - [Karl Appel; Jean-Michel Basquiat; Jose Bedia], 1989, 1999, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - [Jean-Michel Basquiat], 1981-1982 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - [Francois Boisrond.; Kocheisen + Hullman; Shirin Neshat, 1995-2003 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - [Pizzi Cannella; Gian Marco Montesano], 1985-1991 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - [Castelli; Arturo Elizonda; Salomé; Cheri Samba], 1981-1982,1992-2004 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - [Bruno Ceccobelli; Lucia Warck Meister; Marco Tirelli], 1984-1990, 2006 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - [Chicago Art Fair; Basel], 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - [Chuck Connelly], 1984-1986 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - [David Deutsch; Beth Brenner], 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - [Daniele Galliano; Teresa Serrano; Michelle Murcurio], 1988, 1996-2000, 2004 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - [Vincent Gallo], 1985-1991 (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - [K.H. Hodicke; Bernd Koberling; Sal Scarpitta; Jenny Watson], 1981-1992, 2001-2003 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - [Ron Gault Jirado; Tod Wizon], 1985 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - [Barbara Kruger; Jean-Michel Basquiat], 1982-1989 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - [Myriam Laplante; Sabina Mirri; Adriana Varejao; Sy Ross; Manuel Ocampo], 1983-1986, 1994-2003 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - [Helmut Middendorf; Ghada Amer], 1984-1991, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - [Stephen Muller; Frederico Uribe; Scope 2006], 1982-1998, 2002-2006 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - [Nunzio; Nancy Bowen], 1985-1989, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - [Liliana Porter; Pablo Siquier; Fabian Burgos; Graciela Hasper], 1983, 1998-2001 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - [Ira Richer; Guillermo Kuitca; Pietro Fortuna], 1983, 1986, 1990-1992 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - [Mario Schifano; Julio Galan], 1983, 1989-2000 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Subseries G: Acquisition Receipts
    Series comprises receipts for works purchased by Annina Nosei Gallery or by Annina Nosei herself.
    - A, 1981-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - B [1/2], 1976, 1981-1989 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - B [2/2], 1982-1984, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - C, 1983-1989 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - D, 1981-1984, 1989 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - F, 1984-1988 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - G, 1980-1989 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - H, 1979-1982, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - J, 1983-1989 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - K, 1982-1989 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - L, 1979, 1982, 1986-1989 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - M, 1982-1989 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Mc, 1988-1989 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - N, 1982-1987 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - O, 1982,1984 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - P, 1982-1988 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - R, 1983-1985 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - S, 1982-1989 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - T, 1979-1989 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - W, 1979, 1985-1989 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - YZ, 1979, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Subseries H: Invoices
    Subseries is arranged chronologically.